JIANNAN ZHANG (张剑南)

Associate Research Fellow at Sichuan University. I am also employed as a Postdoctoral Fellow in Wang yajun (王亚军) Lab at Sichuan University (四川大学).

I am broadly interested in Avian Physiology, Endocrinology and Metabolism, and Transgenesis in chicken.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

present 2021

Associate Research Fellow

Sichuan University

Sichuan University

• 2021-present, Associate Research Fellow, The College of Life Sciences

present 2017

2021

2017

Post-doctoral Fellow

Sichuan University

Sichuan University

Assistant Research Fellow

Sichuan University

Sichuan University

• 2017-2021, Assistant Research Fellow, The College of Life Sciences



EDUCATION

2017 2011 PhD., Cell Biology

Sichuan University

Sichuan, CN

2011 2007 **B.S.**, National Base of Life Science & Biotechnology Education

Sichuan University

Sichuan, CN

♣ TEACHING EXPERIENCE

2023 2019

Developmental biology (发育生物学)

Undergraduate level class, The College of Life Sciences ♥ Sichuan University

• Undergraduate level class

2021

Cell biology (细胞生物学)

Undergraduate level class, The College of Life Sciences ♥ Sichuan University

• Undergraduate level class



2024 2023

热应激影响家鸡肝脏脂质代谢的调控机制解析(2023NSFSC0230)

主持, CNY ¥200,000, 四川省自然科学基金



CONTACT

- biozhangjn@gmail.com
- github.com/biozhangjn
- **q**q124975496

For more information, please contact me via email.

SKILLS

Wet-lab

- Molecular cloning
- Functional analysis
- IHC/ISH/FISH/Co-IP/Chip-Seq...
- Gene-editing with CRISPR/Cas9
- PGCs culture and Microinjection

Dry-lab

- RNA-Seq data analysis
- scRNA-Seq data analysis
- Highly skilled in R and Bash.

Made with the R package pagedown

Last updated on 2023-01-06.

2021 2020

2021

2019

垂体激素ACTH调控家鸡肝脏糖脂代谢的机制探究 (2020T130439)

主持, CNY ¥180,000, 中国博士后科学基金特别资助

多不饱和脂肪酸调控家鸡肝脏脂肪生成的机制解析(省重)(2019YJ0017)

主持, CNY ¥100,000, 四川省科学技术厅-应用基础研究

家鸡GPR120受体介导多不饱和脂肪酸对肝脏脂质代谢的调节效应探究 (31802056)

主持, CNY ¥300,000, 国家自然科学基金青年项目

PUBLICATIONS

2023

2022

Cholecystokinin (CCK) and its receptors (CCK1R and CCK2R) in chickens: functional analysis and tissue expression

Poultry Science. 2023, 102 (1), 102273. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2022.102273

• Yiping, Wan; Qiuyang, Deng; Zhichun, Zhou; Yue, Deng; **Jiannan, Zhang**; Juan, Li; Yajun, Wang *;

A gene expression atlas of Lohmann white chickens

bioRxiv. 2022. doi: 10.1101/2022.07.30.500160

- Jiannan Zhang[#], Xinglong Wang, Can Lv, Yiping Wan, Xiao Zhang, Juan Li, Yajun Wang
- preprint

Characterization of the Chicken Melanocortin 5 Receptor and its Potential Role in Regulating **Hepatic Glucolipid Metabolism**

Frontiers in physiology. 2022, 2101. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2022.917712

- Xiao Zhang[#], Jiancheng Su[#], Tianjiao Huang, Xinglong Wang, Chenlei Wu, Jing Li, Juan Ll, **Zhang, Jiannan***, Yaiun Wang
- Characterization of CRH-Binding Protein (CRHBP) in chickens: molecular cloning, tissue distribution and investigation of its role as a negative feedback regulator within the hypothalamus-pituitary-adrenal axis

Genes. 2022, 13(10), 1680. doi: 10.3390/genes13101680

- · Yiping Wan, Zheng Zhang, Dongliang Lin, Xinglong Wang, Tianjiao Huang, Jiancheng Su, Jiannan Zhang, Juan Li, Yajun Wang*
- Characterization of Chicken A2A-Adrenoceptor: Molecular Cloning, Functional Analysis, and Its Involvement in Ovarian Follicular Development.

Genes. 2022, 13 (7), 1113. doi: 10.3390/genes12040489

- Jiang, B. #; Cao, B.; Zhou, Z.; Li, Z.; Lv, C.; **Zhang, J.**; Zhang, H.; Wang, Y.; Li, J. *;
- Evidence for Neuropeptide W Acting as a Physiological Corticotropin-Releasing Inhibitory **Factor in Male Chickens**

Endocrinology . 2022, 163 (7), bgac073. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101445

• Liu, M.[#]; Bu, G.[#]; Wan, Y.; **Zhang, J.**; Mo, C.; Li, J.; Wang, Y.^{*};

 LncEDCH1 improves mitochondrial function to reduce muscle atrophy by interacting with SERCA2

Molecular Therapy-Nucleic Acids. 2022, 27: 319-334. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101445

- Cai, B.[#]; Ma, M.[#]; Zhang, J.; Wang, Z.; Kong, S.; Zhou, Z.; Lian, L.; **Zhang, J.**; Li, J.; Wang, Y.; Li, H.^{*}; Zhang, X.; Nie, Q.^{*};
- Impact Factor = 10.18
- Neuropeptide S (NPS) and its receptor (NPSR1) in chickens: cloning, tissue expression, and functional analysis

Poultry Science. 2021, 100 (12), 101445. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2021.101445

- Chao Fang[#], **Jiannan Zhang[#]**, Yiping Wan, Zejiao Li, Feiyang Qi, Yuanhao Dang, Juan Li, Yajun Wang^{*};
- Molecular Cloning and Functional Characterization of Three 5-HT Receptor Genes (HTR1B, HTR1E, and HTR1F) in Chickens

Genes. 2021, 12(6): 891. doi: 10.3390/genes12060891

- Caiyun Sun, Yang Qiu, Qin Ren, Xiao Zhang, Baolong Cao, Yi Zou, Juan Li, **Jiannan Zhang***, Yajun Wang;
- Single-Cell RNA Sequencing Analysis of Chicken Anterior Pituitary: A Bird's-Eye View on Vertebrate Pituitary

Frontiers in physiology. 2021, 12. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2021.562817

- Jiannan Zhang[#], Can Lv[#], Chunheng Mo, Meng Liu, Yiping Wan, Juan Li^{*}, Yajun Wang^{*};
- Impact Factor = 4.566
- Characterization of Four Orphan Receptors (GPR3, GPR6, GPR12 and GPR12L) in Chickens and Ducks and Regulation of GPR12 Expression in Ovarian Granulosa Cells by Progesterone

Genes. 2021, 12(4): 489. doi: 10.3390/genes12040489

- Li, Z.; Jiang, B.; Cao, B.; Zhang, Z.; **Zhang, J.**; Li, J.; Huang, Y.*; Wang, Y.*;
- Characterization of four urotensin II receptors (UTS2Rs) in chickens

Peptides. 2021, 138: 170482. doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2020.170482

- Cui, L.[#], Lv, C.[#], **Zhang, J.**, Li, J.^{*}, & Wang, Y.^{*};
- The Asp298Asn polymorphism of melanocortin-4 receptor (MC4R) in pigs: evidence for its potential effects on MC4R constitutive activity and cell surface expression

Animal Genetics. 2020, 51(5):694-706. doi: 10.1111/age.12986

- **Zhang, J**[#], Li, J[#]; Wu, C; Hu, Z; An, L; Wan, Y; Fang, C; Zhang, X; Li, J^{*}; Wang, Y^{*};
- Impact Factor = 2.841

2021

2020

Melanocortin Receptor 4 (MC4R) Signaling System in Nile Tilapia

International Journal of Molecular Sciences. 2020, 21(19):7036. doi: 10.3390/ijms21197036

- Liu, Tianqiang; Deng, Yue; Zhang, Zheng; Cao, Baolong; Li, Jing; Sun, Caiyun; Hu, Zhixing; **Zhang, Jiannan***; Li, Juan; Wang, Yajun*;
- Impact Factor = 4.556
- Characterization of a novel thyrotropin-releasing hormone receptor, TRHR3, in chickens *Poultry Science*. 2020, 99(3):1643-1654. doi: 10.1016/j.psj.2019.10.062
 - Li, Xiaoxiao[#]; Li, Zhengyang[#]; Deng, Yue; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Li, Juan^{*}; Wang, Yajun^{*};
- Characterization of the neuropeptide FF (NPFF) gene in chickens: evidence for a single bioactive NPAF peptide encoded by the NPFF gene in birds

Domestic Animal Endocrinology. 2020, :106435. doi: 10.1016/j.domaniend.2020.106435

- Chen, J#; Huang, S#; **Zhang, J**; Li, J*; Wang, Y*;
- Arginine vasotocin (AVT)/mesotocin (MT) receptors in chickens: Evidence for the possible involvement of AVT-AVPR1 signaling in the regulation of oviposition and pituitary prolactin expression

General and Comparative Endocrinology. 2019, 281:91-104. doi: 10.1016/j.yqcen.2019.05.013

- Wu, Chao; Lv, Can; Wan, Yiping; Li, Xiaoxiao; **Zhang, Jiannan***; Li, Juan; Wang, Yajun*;
- Regulation of Pituitary Cocaine-and Amphetamine-Regulated Transcript Expression and Secretion by Hypothalamic Gonadotropin-Releasing Hormone in Chickens

Frontiers in physiology. 2019, 10:. doi: 10.3389/fphys.2019.00882

- Mo, Chunheng; Lv, Can; Huang, Long; Li, Zhengyang; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Li, Juan *; Wang, Yajun *;
- Endothelins (EDN1, EDN2, EDN3) and their receptors (EDNRA, EDNRB, EDNRB2) in chickens:
 Functional analysis and tissue distribution

General and comparative endocrinology. 2019, 283:113231. doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2019.113231

- Liu, Haikun; Luo, Qin; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Mo, Chunheng; Wang, Yajun *; Li, Juan *;
- Identification of a Novel Functional Corticotropin-Releasing Hormone (CRH2) in Chickens and Its Roles in Stimulating Pituitary TSHβ Expression and ACTH Secretion

Frontiers in Endocrinology. 2019, 10:595. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2019.00595

- Bu, Guixian[#]; Fan, Jie[#]; Yang, Ming; Lv, Can; Lin, Yin; Li, Jinxuan; Meng, Fengyan; Du, Xiaogang; Zeng, Xianyin^{*}; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Juan Li; Yajun Wang^{*}
- Characterization of the Apelin/Elabela Receptors (APLNR) in Chickens, Turtles, and Zebrafish:
 Identification of a Novel Apelin-Specific Receptor in Teleosts

Frontiers in endocrinology. 2018, 9:756. doi: 10.3389/fendo.2018.00756

• **Zhang, Jiannan**; Zhou, Yawei; Wu, Chenlei; Wan, Yiping; Fang, Chao; Li, Jing; Fang, Wenqian; Yi, Ran; Zhu, Guogiang: Li, Juan *: Yaiun Wang *

2019

2018

 The orphan G protein-coupled receptor 25 (GPR25) is activated by Apelin and Apela in nonmammalian vertebrates

Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications. 2018, 501(2):408-414. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2018.04.229

- **Zhang, Jiannan**[#]; Wan, Yiping[#]; Fang, Chao; Chen, Junan; Ouyang, Wangan; Li, Juan ^{*}; Wang, Yajun ^{*};
- Characterization of neuromedin U (NMU), neuromedin S (NMS) and their receptors (NMUR1, NMUR2) in chickens

Peptides. 2018, 101:69-81. doi: 10.1016/j.peptides.2017.12.022

- Wan, Yiping[#]; **Zhang, Jiannan**[#]; Fang, Chao; Chen, Junan; Li, Jing; Li, Juan ^{*}; Wu, Chenlei; Wang, Yajun ^{*};
- The interaction of MC3R and MC4R with MRAP2, ACTH, α-MSH and AgRP in chickens *Journal of Endocrinology*. 2017, 234(2):155-174. doi: 10.1530/JOE-17-0131
 - **Zhang, Jiannan**; Li, Xin; Zhou, Yawei; Cui, Lin; Li, Jing; Wu, Chenlei; Wan, Yiping; Li, Juan *; Wang, Yajun *;
 - Impact Factor = 4.706
- Molecular characterization of neuropeptide Y (NPY) receptors (Y1, Y4 and Y6) and investigation of the tissue expression of their ligands (NPY, PYY and PP) in chickens General and comparative endocrinology. 2017, 240:46-60. doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2016.09.005
 - Gao, Shunyu[#]; **Zhang, Jiannan**[#]; He, Chen; Meng, Fengyan; Bu, Guixian; Zhu, Guoqiang; Li, Juan ^{*}; Wang, Yajun ^{*};
- Characterization of melanin-concentrating hormone (MCH) and its receptor in chickens:
 Tissue expression, functional analysis, and fasting-induced up-regulation of hypothalamic
 MCH expression

Gene. 2017, 615:57-67. doi: 10.1016/j.gene.2017.03.009

- Cui, Lin; Lv, Can; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Mo, Chunheng; Lin, Dongliang; Li, Juan *; Wang, Yajun *;
- Molecular characterization of three NPY receptors (Y2, Y5 and Y7) in chickens: Gene structure, tissue expression, promoter identification, and functional analysis

General and Comparative Endocrinology. 2016, 236:24-34. doi: 10.1016/j.ygcen.2016.04.019

- He, Chen[#]; **Zhang, Jiannan**[#]; Gao, Shunyu; Meng, Fengyan; Bu, Guixian; Li, Juan ^{*}; Wang, Yajun ^{*};
- Identification and characterization of the free fatty acid receptor 2 (FFA2) and a novel functional FFA2-like receptor (FFA2L) for short-chain fatty acids in pigs: Evidence for the existence of a duplicated FFA2 gene (FFA2L) in some mammalian species

Domestic animal endocrinology. 2014, 47:108-118. e1. doi: 10.1016/j.domaniend.2013.10.004

• **Zhang, J**; Cheng, S; Wang, Y *; Yu, X; Li, J *;

2017

2016

2014

 Synthesis and biological evaluation of novel benzamide derivatives as potent smoothened antagonists

Bioorganic & medicinal chemistry letters. 2014, 24(5):1426-1431. doi: 10.1016/j.bmcl.2014.01.006

- Wu, Tian-Ming; Wang, Dao-Cai; Xiang, Pu; **Zhang, Jian-Nan**; Sang, Ya-Xiong; Lin, Hong-Jun; Chen, Jie; Xie, Gang; Song, Hang; Zhao, Ying-Lan *;
- Glucagon-like peptide (GCGL) is a novel potential TSH-releasing factor (TRF) in Chickens: I)
 Evidence for its potent and specific action on stimulating TSH mRNA expression and secretion in the pituitary

Endocrinology. 2014, 155(11):4568-4580. doi: 10.1210/en.2014-1331

• Huang, Guian; He, Chen; Meng, Fengyan; Li, Juan; **Zhang, Jiannan**; Wang, Yajun *;

CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

黑皮质素系统在家鸡能量平衡中的作用机理解析

四川省细胞生物学会2017年度学术大会

2017

2011

◆ Chengdu, CN

● 家鸡促甲状腺激素受体(cTSHR)的克隆、剪切变体鉴定及其功能分析

第十六次全国动物遗传育种学术讨论会系列学术报告会

♀ Yangzhou, CN